创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning, there was darkness,
随着一声爆炸
and then, bang--
诞生了无尽膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在揭秘这个诡异
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
震撼 神秘莫测的
the mind-blowing, the deadly secrets
地方 - 我们所谓的《宇宙》
of a place we call "The Universe."
曲速
Warp speed,
输送器
transporters,
虫洞
wormholes,
激光武器 -
and laser blasters--
科幻发明
science fiction concepts.
然而它们有现实基础吗？
But are they grounded in reality?
是否有生命存在？ 回答是肯定的
Is there life out there? The answer is yes.
现在下一代物理学家
Now the next generation of physicists
致力于重写宇宙规则手册
work to rewrite the cosmic rule book.
我不一定将自己局限在我们现在所掌握的物理学里
I can't necessarily limit myself by the physics we know today.
似乎数十年前的未来派
And what seemed futuristic just decades ago
就可能很快前往你附近的星球
may be coming soon to a planet near you.
接近光速出行的人
Someone traveling close to the speed of light
实际上能够跳入未来
can effectively jump into the future.
下一站 明天
Next stop: tomorrow
抵达今天
arriving today,
让我们一起去探索科学幻想和科学事实的世界
as we explore the worlds of science fiction and science fact.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：HDC字幕组 调校：晴天 招募Q号: 76846146
历史频道 - 宇宙 第4季第11集 科幻与科学事实
The History Channel - The Universe s04e11 Science Fiction,Science Fact
科学幻想探索新生命 新文明
Science fiction explores new life, new civilizations,
以及遥远的星系
and galaxies far, far away.
飞行汽车及激光束的神奇未来
The fantastic future of flying cars and laser beams
似乎依然是遥不可及的光鲜的海市蜃楼
still seems like a shimmering mirage of a tomorrow that never came.
路在何方？
Roads?
我们要去的地方 我想我们还是需要有路可走的
Where we're going, I think we'll still need some roads.
不过有那么一些科幻技术
But then there are those sci-fi technologies
可以让你走得比想得快
which may be arriving sooner than you think.
约会迟到了？
Running late for an appointment?
堵在路上了？
Stuck in traffic?
科幻有了你出行问题的解决方案
Science fiction has the answer for your transportation problems.
只要从地点A发送到
Simply beam from point A
地点B
to point B.
《星际迷航》里的输送器是那些东西之一
The "Star Trek" transporter is one of those things
我们谁都可以进行大量飞行
that any of us who do a lot of flying
但愿快点发明出来吧
really wish would just please be invented.
但是当你着手考虑所需的技术时
But then when you start thinking about the technologies required,
它就有点令人生畏了
it becomes a bit daunting.
在《星际迷航》里 如我们在演出中所描述的
On "Star Trek," as we've depicted it on the show,
输送器的工作是将人拆成一颗颗原子
the transporter works by taking a person apart atom by atom,
将那些原子转换成能量束
converting those atoms into a stream of energy,
将那能量发送到目的地
beaming that energy to the target location,
然后在目的地
and then reassembling all of those atoms
把所有的原子重组成人
that make up the person at the target location.
在它们扫描人体的过程中
As they're scanning the person,
会记录下状态 所有的原子
they're recording the positions of all the atoms,
所有围绕原子的电子
of all the electrons orbiting the atoms,
所有电子的自旋
of the spins of all of the electrons,
体内分子结构的波函数
the wave functions of all of the molecular structures in the body,
所有东西的振荡 运动 速度
how everything's vibrating, moving, the velocities.
数据量非常庞大
The amount of data is enormous,
然而它们设法仔细地全部扫描
and somehow they're scanning all of it remotely,
然后它们设法将人体拆解
and then they're somehow taking and tearing that body apart.
将人转成纯粹的能所需的能量将远超过
The amount of energy required to turn a human into pure energy would be
人类迄今制造的最强大的核武器里的能量
far more than in the most powerful nuclear weapons that humans have ever made.
其过程本身将是毁灭性的
The process itself would be destructive.
要将我这般大小的人整个转换为能量
To convert someone my size entirely to energy
将相当于地球上引爆过的最大的核弹
would be the equivalent 41 times the energy release
所释放能量的41倍
of the largest nuclear weapon ever exploded on planet Earth.
我的意思是 如果你现在就想传送我
I mean, if you tried to transport me right now,
你就得扪心自问一下
you have to ask yourself
然而传送器传送另一头出来的是什么？
But what comes out the other side of a transporter beam?
是你么
Is it you,
还是你的完美量子复制品呢？
or a perfect quantum replica of you?
它们是将人分解并重组呢
Are they disassembling the person and reassembling them,
还是把人分解后 储存信息
or are they disassembling the person, storing the information,
然后在从头重新创造人呢？
and recreating the person from scratch?
这是个有趣的问题
It's an interesting question.
传送器究竟是把你杀死 然后造出一个克隆人呢
Does the transporter actually kill you and then create a clone,
还是它设法维持你 将你传送到别的地方呢？
or does it somehow preserve you and transport you to another place?
要是你说 你被分解成一颗颗原子
If you're going to say that you're disassembled atom by atom,
被转换成了能量束
converted into an energy stream,
然后再别的地方进行重组
and then reassembled someplace else,
我看不出 它相比杀死你然后再复活你
I don't see how that's anything other than killing you
有何不同
and resurrecting you.
它可能是来源于科幻的装置
It may be a device rooted in science fiction,
但是传送技术在现实世界里的前景
but the real-world prospects for transporter technology
已引起了美国军方的注意
attracted the attention of the U.S. military.
空军展开了一项研究
The Air Force commissioned a study
研究未来的物质传送系统
to investigate the future of matter transmission systems,
不足为奇 遇上了一些障碍
and, not surprisingly, found a number of roadblocks.
开发有效的传送器是个难题
Developing a working transporter is a tough nut.
最大的问题之一
Among the biggest,
你可能已经苦恼于自己的家用电脑 -
a problem you may have struggled with on your home computer--
没有足够的硬盘空间
not enough hard drive space.
别再考虑兆字节或千兆字节了
Forget megabytes or gigabytes.
仅仅扫描一个人所创建的信息
The information created by a scan of just one person
就会产生数十亿兆兆字节
would generate billions of terabytes.
一个人用TB硬盘来储存
One person would take roughly enough terabyte drives' worth of storage
足以填满5亿个帝国大厦
to fill 500 million Empire State Buildings.
把个人储存为数据的含义就是
And the implication of storing a person as data is,
你是否必须立刻传送它们？
do you have to teleport them immediately?
要是你把它们非物质化 储存为信息
What if you dematerialize them, store the information,
保存50年 100年 5000年又当如何呢？
and save it for 50 years, 100 years, 5,000 years?
从那个人的角度
From the point of view of that person,
就变成了时间旅行了
it becomes time travel.
如果硬盘的容量在目前的水平上继续改善的话
If hard drive capacities continue to improve at their present rate,
处理储存需求的驱动能力就有可能存续
a drive capable of handling the storage requirements may exist
约200到300年
in about 200 to 300 years.
打造物质传送器的最后一个障碍
A final barrier to creating a matter transporter
是量子物理学的一个基本属性
is a fundamental property of quantum physics,
叫做海森堡的测不准原理
known as Heisenberg's Uncertainty Principle.
在最早的《星际迷航》首映之后
After the original "Star Trek" premiered,
很多物理学家纷纷质疑传送技术
a lot of physicists questioned the transporter technology,
他们谈论的最大的问题之一
and one of the biggest problems with it that they talked about
就是确实不可能完全精确地同时掌握
was that it's really not possible to know with complete precision
原子或亚原子粒子的位置和动量
both the location and the momentum of an atom or a subatomic particle.
换句话说 你对物体的位置掌握越多
In other words, the more you know where something is,
那你对其速度的掌握就越少 反之亦然
the less you know how fast it's going and vice versa.
来拍一张旋转木马的照片
Take a picture of the merry-go-round.
好 你无疑能看到旋转木马
Well, you can certainly see where that merry-go-round is
相对附近其它东西的位置
with respect to anything else that's nearby,
但问题是旋转木马的旋转就有点模糊了
but the things that are spinning on the merry-go-round are kind of blurred.
如果你想重组零零碎碎的东西
If you're trying to reassemble the bits and pieces
来构建已经非物质化了的柯克船长量子形象
that make up a quantum image of a just-dematerialized Captain Kirk,
你最不愿意看到的事情就是海森堡的量子不确定性
the last thing you want is Heisenberg's quantum uncertainty.
在《星际旅行 下一代》里
In "Star Trek: The Next Generation,"
我们的技术顾问之一 迈克 奥库达
one of our technical advisors, Mike Okuda,
想出了这个叫做海森堡补偿器的主意
came up with the idea of this thing called a Heisenberg compensator,
那是传送器的组件
which is the component in the transporter
方便地处理那个小问题
that conveniently deals with that little problem.
我一直认为那是个很聪明的解决方案 -
And I always thought that was a very clever solution to--
针对建造传送器的最大的障碍之一
to one of the biggest obstacles in building a transporter.
传送器有时会发生故障
The transporter would, on occasion, break down,
那在人的传送中一般是很不好的
and that was generally not good for the person being transported.
如果有数据在传送过程中丢失
If some data were lost during transport,
你最后就会缺眼少脑什么的
and you ended up without eyes or a brain or something,
那显然是个灾难
that would obviously be disastrous.
你可能会丢失一些DNA
You might lose a bit from your DNA,
虽然你的身体具有DNA修复机能
and while your body has DNA repair mechanisms,
但无数次修复有可能会导致癌症
that repeated numerous times could lead to cancers.
它会导致畸形
It could lead to deformities.
它会导致各种毛病
It could lead to all sorts of maladies
那是你真的可能不愿意涉及的
that you really probably wouldn't want to deal with.
超大规模超级计算机
Massively huge supercomputers,
海森堡补偿器
Heisenberg compensators,
量子扫描 -
quantum scanning--
科幻的方方面面
all part of science fiction.
那么我们如何才能使其成为科学事实呢？
So how do we make it science fact?
通过来一点幽灵
By getting a little spooky.
爱因斯坦著名的将其称为 超距幽灵作用
Einstein famously called it "spooky action at a distance."
那是怪异的量子纠缠世界
It's the bizarre world of quantum entanglement.
基本上 两个粒子会以这样的方式互动
Basically, two particles can interact in such a way
在它们分开时
that when they become separated,
一个状态会直接影响到另一个的状态
the state of one directly affects the state of the other.
利用这种纠缠属性
And using this property of entanglement,
你可以操控一个地方
you can manipulate one location
来瞬间改变另一个地方的情况
to change what's going on in the other location instantaneously.
这就是出自量子力学的一个最诡异的东西
This is about the single freakiest thing to come out of quantum mechanics.
没办法把信息从一个粒子传给另一个粒子
There's no way for the information to travel from the one particle to the other.
你可以将它们分开到的距离
You can separate them by so much
是如果你进行测量 连光速都不会让信息
that even the speed of light doesn't allow the information
从一点到另外一点
to get from one point to the other when you make the measurement.
整个地球上或许就三个人
There's probably three people on the entire planet
完全理解这个概念
that fully understand this concept,
我们其余的人就看着运算
and the rest of us just look at the mathematics
浑身不舒服
and get queasy.
计划中的纠缠幽灵作用的测试安排
Plans are in the works to test the spooky action of entanglement
是通过地面与低地球轨道间的传送信息
by transmitting information between the ground and low Earth orbit,
人类史上的首次发送
the first "beaming up" In human history.
该技术会被利用在
This technology could be put to use in
新一代的超级计算机的研发之中
the development of a new generation of supercomputers,
计算机可能会有朝一日快到足以
computers that may one day be fast enough
执行复杂计算以满足更加尖端的传送器的需求
to carry out the complex calculations needed for a more sophisticated transporter.
我会立马使用传送器的 前提是我要确保
I would use a transporter in an instant if I were assured
我可以回到家里与亲人团聚
that I could return home to my loved ones when I so desired.
我认为那将是个奇妙之旅
I think it would be a fantastic trip.
在J J 艾布拉姆斯重启的《星际迷航》系列中
In J.J. Abrams' reboot of the "Star Trek" franchise,
坏人以全新的方式用作了科幻的主角
the villain used a science fiction staple in a whole new way,
把黑洞作为武器
using a black hole as a weapon.
我喜欢新的《星际迷航》电影
I love the new "Star Trek" movie.
我喜欢它们进入的方式
I love the direction they've gone in,
但黑洞伤透了我的脑筋 就像物理学那样
but the black hole just broke the part of my brain that likes physics.
黑洞是太空中的区域
Black holes are regions in space
那里 物质被压缩得非常厉害
where matter has been compressed so much
局部引力异常强大 任何东西
that the local gravity is so strong that nothing,
甚至是光 都无法逃脱
not even light, can escape.
要是你可以将一个黑洞投入行星的核心
If you could drop a black hole into the core of a planet
完完了 它将会聚爆
gone. It would implode.
控制黑洞简直是不可能的
Controlling a black hole is nigh-impossible,
因为要是你企图操控它 你也会完蛋的
because if you try to manipulate it you would also implode.
在《星际迷航》电影里
In the "Star Trek" film,
一些外来的物质形式 它们叫做红物质
some exotic form of matter that they called red matter
被用来启动黑洞形成在
was used to initiate the formation of a black hole
现存行星的核心
inside the core of an existing planet.
你通常是不会利用一些红粘液
You aren't generally going to collapse a planet into a black hole
将行星塌缩成黑洞的
using any amount of red slime.
那就是不会发生的
It's just not going to happen.
当然啦 在科学事实里
Of course, in science fact,
我们近来有自己对黑洞的担忧
we recently had our own concerns about black holes
可能性就在对知识的追求中
and the possibility that in a quest for knowledge,
我们的星球会被抹去
our planet could be obliterated,
被吸进我们所创造的黑洞贪得无厌的肚子里
sucked into the insatiable maw of a black hole we created.
在科幻中
In science fiction,
诸如J J 艾布拉姆斯的首部《星际迷航》电影
such as J.J. Abrams' first "Star Trek" movie,
行星中心创造出来的黑洞
a black hole created at the center of a planet
造成了屏幕上60亿火神人的死亡
caused the on-screen deaths of 6 billion Vulcans.
该行星将成为黑洞质量的一部分
That planet would become part of the mass of the black hole.
它会被撕成碎片
It would be ripped to shreds
从我们的宇宙中永远消失
and disappear from our universe forever.
所以它就是终极末日武器
So it is kind of the ultimate doomsday weapon.
在科学事实里
In science fact,
地球这里将亚原子粒子撞击在一起的打算
plans to smash subatomic particles together here on Earth
引发了担心 如果粒子
raised fears that if the particles
碰撞时速度够快的话
were going fast enough when they collided,
它们就会形成黑洞 摧毁我们的星球
they could form a black hole, destroying our planet.
有在瑞士的欧洲核子研究中心建造的新工厂
The new facility that's been built by CERN in Switzerland,
大型强子对撞机
the Large Hadron Collider,
旨在探索物质的基本属性
is designed to explore the fundamental nature of matter,
将原子撞在一起 这样你就可以将它们打碎
to smash atoms together so that you can break them apart
来看看其基本构件
and see what the fundamental building blocks are.
比如 他们想找到所谓的希格斯玻色子
For example, they want to find the so-called Higgs boson,
它被认为是把质量赋予其它所有粒子
which is thought to give mass to all other particles,
但它们也有可能产生迷你黑洞
but they also might produce miniature black holes.
地球上的黑洞？
Black holes on Earth?
人类往往认为黑洞
Humans tend to view black holes
是不停旋转 吞噬物质的大漩涡
as large swirling, matter-sucking vortexes
任何东西 甚至光都无法逃逸
from which nothing, not even light, can escape.
正在瑞士形成黑洞的想法敲响了警钟
The idea of one forming in Switzerland set off alarm bells.
不过科学家向紧张的公众保证
But scientists assured a nervous public
所形成的任何黑洞都是微观的
any black holes formed would be microscopic.
小黑洞会瞬间蒸发
Tiny little black holes would instantaneously evaporate,
然而仍然会存在极短的时间
yet, nevertheless, would exist for a very, very short time.
那种情况的概率是很小的
Probability of that happening is small,
即使我们创造出了一个微观黑洞
and even if we did create a microscopic black hole,
它也不是那种会钻入地球中心
it's not something that would sink to the center of the Earth
从内向外吞噬我们星球的东西
and start devouring our planet from the inside out.
黑洞是如何长大的呢？
How does a black hole grow?
来看看纸棒在棉花糖机里
Think of a paper stick going round and round
绕圈的情况
on the inside of a cotton candy machine.
随着纸棒采集材料 会长得越来越大
As the stick gathers material it grows bigger and bigger,
就像黑洞吞噬物质的过程
just as a black hole does when it sucks in matter.
那么微观黑洞呢？
But a microscopic black hole?
首先 情况是它吸得极其缓慢
The first thing that happens is it eats the stick very, very slowly.
事实上 在一年的过程中
In fact, in the course of a year,
饥饿 愤怒的小微观黑洞
a hungry, angry little microscopic black hole
可能就吃下100个质子
might eat a hundred protons.
由于吸管逐渐远离 由于漩涡的蒸发要快于
And with the stick going away, with the vortex evaporating faster
它吸进供成长的新物质
than it can suck in new material to grow,
所以微观黑洞就只能消失了
the microscopic black hole simply disappears.
黑洞并非我们需要担心的东西
Black holes aren't something that we need to worry about.
事实上 就有超大质量黑洞
In fact, there's a supermassive black hole
在我们银河系的中心
sitting right in the center of our own Milky Way Galaxy,
埋头干自己的活
minding its own business,
群星高兴地围绕着它周而复始
with stars happily orbiting it round after round after round.
你实际上可以看到黑洞周围
You can actually see around the black holes
附近星系盘里的某些物质正遭破坏
in some of the nearby galaxies disks of material getting destroyed
在其旋入时 会变得非常炙热和致密
as it spirals in, and it gets so hot and so dense
在其旋入时 会发出大量的光
as it spirals in that it gives off massive amounts of light.
如果科幻作家想像坏蛋那样利用黑洞的话
If sci-fi writers want to make use of black holes as the bad guy,
这里就有一个科学准确的方法来达到目的
there is a scientifically accurate way to do so.
在我看来用得还不够的奇思妙想的装置之一
One of the interesting plot devices that isn't used enough in my opinion
就是把黑洞作为太阳系的破坏装置
is the black hole as destructor of the solar system.
会有一些小黑洞在外头
There could be some small black hole out there
在与我们太阳系碰撞的过程中
on a collision course with our solar system,
我们看不到它
and we wouldn't see it
直到它碰上奥尔特云
until it started to interact with the Oort cloud,
冰冻的云
the cloud of frozen stuff
来自外太阳系的彗星
that comets come from in the outer solar system.
它可能就在碰撞的过程中
It could just be on a collision course,
等待着摧毁我们整个太阳系
waiting to destroy our entire solar system,
直到地球末日来临的前几年才被发现
invisible until a few years away from the Earth's doom.
我们或许首先注意到的是奥尔特云开始闪烁
The first thing we'd probably notice is the Oort cloud starting to flicker
因为高能粒子
with high-energy particles
如小冰粒开始被吸进去了
as little bits of ice start to get sucked in.
接着我们会注意到
Then we'd start to notice
外太阳系的轨道开始变形
the outer solar system's orbits getting deformed.
然后轨道变形的数量
And then the amount of deformation of orbits
会波及到我们的地球
would increase as our own planet Earth,
这取决于黑洞出现在太阳的哪一边
depending on which side of the Sun the black hole was coming in from,
不是开始拉向太阳
either started to get pulled toward the Sun
就是拉出太阳
or pulled out from the Sun
使我们不是死于火就是死于冰
causing us to die either by fire or ice,
我个人并不认为哪个好些
and I personally don't think either is nice.
地球毁灭是科幻的流行主题
The destruction of the Earth is a popular theme in science fiction,
对地球生存的威胁有好多种形式
with threats to the planet's existence coming in many forms.
来看电影《绝世天劫》
Take the movie "Armageddon."
一颗德州般大的小行星正砸向我们地球
An asteroid the size of Texas is bearing down on our planet.
在这部灾难片里
In this disaster movie,
科学就成了真正的灾难
it's the science which is the real disaster.
我想所有科学家都会认同 世界末日 噢 天哪
I think any scientist will agree that, "Armageddon," oh, my gosh,
科学幻想只是名义而已
science fiction in name only.
大量的虚构 不是大量的科学
Lot of fiction, not a lot of science.
看他们所描绘的 这颗小行星行将撞上地球
The way they depicted this asteroid that was going to impact the Earth
他们又如何来应对威胁
and how they dealt with that threat
通过发送航天飞机 利用核装置
by sending up a space shuttle and using nuclear devices was
真是荒谬
was ridiculous.
由此带来的问题是现在 并不是一颗小行星
The problem with that is now, instead of having one asteroid
行将摧毁地球一部分
that's going to destroy one part of the planet,
而是你有了成千上万甚至数百万个小行星碎片
you have thousands and maybe millions of chunks of asteroid
行将毁灭地球的大部分
that are going to destroy large parts of the planet.
没错 炸毁小行星 - 实在很糟糕
Yeah, blowing up asteroids-- really, really bad.
你要设法将它们移走 而不是将其炸毁
You want to move them somehow, not blow them up.
但要是地球命在旦夕了
But if Earth bites the big one,
我们就需要有新地方来定居了
we'll need a new place to live.
地球化的概念就是你有火星那样的世界
The idea of terraforming is you take a world like Mars
目前并没有能力维持生命
that isn't currently capable of supporting life
行走于其地表
just walking around on its surface,
你改变其环境
and you alter the environment,
你某种程度改变行星本身
you alter the planet itself in a way
使得人类能随便生存于其表面
that allows human life to exist casually on the surface.
把火星变成一个地方
Make Mars into a place
我们可以不用宇航服就能呼吸
where we can breathe without a spacesuit,
我们可以穿着舒适的夏装站在户外
where we can stand outside in our comfortable summer clothes
创造一个全新的世界供我们生活
and create a whole new world for us to live on.
这将是个惊人之举
This would be a pretty phenomenal thing to do,
但是他们认为 那并非做不到
but, they think, not impossible.
我们太阳系里的新行星被人类称为家园的
A new planet in our solar system for humans to call home,
只是以防地球整个报废
just in case the Earth gets all used up.
要是我们整个物种的生存要依靠它时
If our survival as a species depended on it,
如何才能将红色星球变蓝呢？
just what would it take to turn the Red Planet blue?
火星是一个红色 贫瘠的不毛之地
Mars is a red, barren, desolate world.
冰冻的原野 陡峭的悬崖
Freezing plains and sheer cliffs,
冻土层深埋地下
a permafrost layer embedded in the surface,
巨大的火山 干涸的河床
massive volcanoes and dry river beds
暗示了该星球湿润的过去
that hint at the planet's watery past.
因为火星非常类似于地球
Because Mars is so similar to Earth,
地球化火星的想法
the idea of terraforming Mars
几十年来在科幻中已暂露头角
has come up in science fiction for decades.
不过要让火星再次生息
But to make Mars live and breathe again,
这个冰凉的荒原将要经历大规模的全球变暖
this frozen wasteland will have to undergo a massive global warming.
地球化火星的一个关键要素
A key ingredient for terraforming Mars
就是把所有的固体二氧化碳 干冰
is to get all the solid carbon dioxide, the dry ice,
取出火星土壤 进入大气层
out of Mars' soil and into the atmosphere.
那会产生较高的气压
That would create higher pressures.
也会产生某种温室效应
It would also produce some greenhouse warming,
升高温度
raising temperatures.
那要走过很长的路
That would go a long way
才能使其更加适合于生命
toward making it more sustainable for life.
火星的极冠之一
One of the polar caps of Mars
几乎是由冰冻的二氧化碳构成
is comprised mostly of frozen carbon dioxide.
假如我们能够设法加热该极冠
If we could somehow heat up that polar cap
释放出二氧化碳
and release that carbon dioxide
将它放回大气层
and put it back into the atmosphere,
那么你就开启了增厚火星大气层的进程了
then you would start a process of thickening the atmosphere of Mars.
那将是朝着地球化的第一步
That would be the first step toward terraforming it.
方法之一就是安放一大堆卫星
One way would be to put up a bunch of satellites
收集太阳能并聚焦到火星上
that would collect the Sun's energy and focus them in on Mars.
那基本上会被地表所吸收
That would basically be absorbed by the surface,
会蒸发那些冰
it would go into evaporating those ices,
将它们释放出来
would free them up
那样它们就会形成大气层了
so that they form atmospheric gases.
人们还可以将大量黑色材料放在
One could also put a bunch of dark material
火星的极地冰冠上
on the frozen polar ice caps of Mars.
那种黑色材料将会吸收而不是反射
That dark material would absorb rather than reflect
较多的太阳辐射
more of the Sun's radiation,
这样就使得那材料及下面的冰
thus allowing that material and the ices underneath
得到加热并蒸发那些冰
to heat up and evaporate those ices.
在为人类居住而对火星地球化时
When terraforming Mars for human habitation,
有一个关键要素是你不能忽视的
there's one key ingredient you can't overlook.
地球有一个较强的磁场
Earth has a fairly strong magnetic field.
磁场保护我们抵御太阳风
That magnetic field protects us from solar wind.
太阳流出的带电粒子
Charged particles streaming out from the Sun
被地球的磁场绕开了地球
are shunted around Earth by Earth's magnetic field.
火星并没有那东西
Mars doesn't have that.
任何试图居住其表面的人
Anybody who tried to live on the surface
都会让自己的身体 自己的个头
would have their body, their mass,
持续遭遇到太阳辐射的攻击
constantly impinged upon by radiation from the Sun.
火星度假之旅依然是科幻
Taking a vacation trip to Mars is still science fiction.
不过人类一直在拉近
But mankind continues to draw closer to the day
地球飞船能翱翔我们太阳系的日子
when ships from Earth will zip around our solar system.
在我们自己的太阳系里逛逛相对较为容易
It's relatively easy to get around within our own solar system.
40年前 我们造访了月球
40 years ago, we traveled to the Moon.
我们已派送航天器去我们太阳系里所有的行星
We've sent spacecraft to all of the other planets in our solar system.
距离以数百万或者数十亿来计
The distances are measured in millions or billions of miles.
那是本地的太空旅行
That's local space travel.
星际旅行将有极大的不同
Interstellar travel is something much different.
物理学给我们的一个非常现实的问题
One of the very real problems that physics gives us
就是光速的限制
is the limitation of the speed of light.
说起超光速旅行
When it comes to faster-than-light travel,
传统的物理学家一直就是一个声音 -
traditionally physicists have been speaking with one voice--
没辙 阿门
"No way. So say we all."
但为何光速是宇宙速度的极限呢？
But why is the speed of light a universal speed limit?
那是我们的观众想问《宇宙》节目的问题
That's what one of our viewers wanted to ask "The Universe,"
所以他们写给我们的网站 -
so they wrote to us on our website
为什么物体的速度不能超过光速呢？
Why can't something travel faster than the speed of light?
是啊 有好多人问过我这个问题
Well, a lot of people ask me that question.
那是个幸运儿
It's a favorite.
你就是无法从这里到那里 用快于光的速度
You just can't get from here to there at a speed faster than that of light
除非你没有质量
unless you're massless.
我们必须搞明白如何去处理的问题之一就是
One of the problems we have to figure out how to deal with is,
我们跑得越快 基本上我们的质量会随之增加
as we go faster, essentially our mass increases,
这就需要越来越多的能量来提高我们的速度
and it takes more and more energy to increase our velocity.
唯有光 光子没有质量
Only light, photons with no mass,
能够达到光的速度
can go at the speed of light,
但任何具有质量的东西
but anything that has mass
都需要无穷的能量
would require an infinite amount of energy
才能够达到那么快
to get going that fast.
那是无法达到的 是不可能的
It can't be done. It's impossible.
在科幻中 这不是个问题
In science fiction, this isn't a problem.
就发明一些灵巧的未来科技来对付它
Just invent some handy bit of futuristic tech to deal with it.
锂晶体派啥用场？
What are dilithium crystals for?
它们不能做什么？
What aren't they for?
锂晶体能让曲速引擎跑起来
Dilithium crystals make the warp engine go.
那就是我们对此要说的一切
That's all we need to say about it.
有各种名称
There are various names
给予了那种种科技
that have been given to these kinds of technologies:
超空间引擎
hyperdrive,
超光速推进器
superluminal drive,
星际之门
stargates.
越来越多的科学家在成长过程中
More and more, scientists who've grown up
眼看着自己的英雄在星系里跑来跑去
watching their heroes whiz around the galaxy
似乎不愿意断然否定超光速旅行
seem unwilling to flatly dismiss the possibility of faster-than-light travel.
有位科学家 名叫米给尔 阿库别瑞
A scientist named Miguel Alcubierre
提出了一个用于曲速引擎的理论概念
came up with a theoretical notion for a warp drive
它需要扩张你飞船身后的空间
that would involve expanding space behind your starship
压缩你飞船前面的空间
and contracting it in front of your starship.
物理学里 爱因斯坦或别人的理论里没有提及
And there was nothing in physics, in Einstein's theory or anybody else's,
称空间本身
that says that space itself
不能扩展或压缩会快于光速
cannot stretch or be squeezed faster than the speed of light.
事实上 我们认为那在宇宙诞生时确实发生过
In fact, we think that's exactly what happened when the universe was born.
空间的扩展在大爆炸后的百万分之一秒里
Space expanded much, much faster than the speed of light
要比光速快许多许多
in the microseconds after the Big Bang,
一直延伸到我们今天所见到的我们周围的宇宙
leading to the universe that we see around us today.
因此 如果你有足够的能量
So, if you had enough energy,
你就可以以百倍光速来扩展你身后的空间
you could conceivably expand space behind you at a hundred times the speed of light,
以百倍光速来压缩你前面的空间
and squeeze space in front of you at a hundred times the speed of light,
实际上就是以百倍光速旅行
and, in effect, be traveling at a hundred times the speed of light,
虽然是在你自己的小空间气泡里
even though in your own little bubble of space,
不过你永远都不会超过光速
you're never traveling faster than the speed of light.
现实生活中的宇航员想迅速抵达某处
When a real-life astronaut wants to get somewhere in a hurry,
选项是相当有限的
the options are rather limited.
如今的大多数航天器都是用液体燃料和固体燃料
Most spacecraft today use liquid fuel and solid fuel.
航天飞机所使用的固体燃料助推器
The space shuttle uses solid fuel boosters
就好象是一个大冲天炮
that are kind of like a big bottle rocket.
一旦你将它点燃 它就起飞了
Once you light them off, they're going.
同时 你还有化学火箭
On the other hand, you also have chemical rockets.
很简单的类型就是液态氢和液态氧
A very simple type would be liquid hydrogen and liquid oxygen.
你只要将它们放在一起 - 巨大的能量
You just run them together-- huge amount of energy.
副产品是水和大量的热量
The byproduct's water and a whole lot of heat.
现在新一代神太空探测器
Now the latest generation of deep-space probes
依赖全新的科技
relies on entirely new technology,
直接出自科幻经典小说里 -
lifted straight from the pages of classic sci-fi stories--
离子驱动器
ion drives.
就是你基本上将原子
This is where you basically take atoms,
剥离一些电子
strip off a few electrons,
最后形成带电粒子
and you end up with a charged particle.
用磁场来加速它
Accelerate it with a magnetic field
将这些高速粒子送出航天器的尾部
and send these high-velocity particles out one end of the spacecraft.
其与化学引擎的区别
The difference between that and chemical engines
在于有了离子引擎 你就有了很低很低的推力
is that with an ion engine you have very, very low thrust.
产生同样推力的离子引擎
An ion engine generates the same amount of thrust
就这张纸的重量
as the weight of this piece of paper,
但它一次可以用上几个月
but it does so for months at a time.
由于恒定 虽然很小 但经过数月的加速
And with constant, albeit small, acceleration for months,
你就可以得到相当高的速度
you can get up to some pretty high speeds.
航天局的黎明号航天器正利用离子动力
NASA's Dawn spacecraft is using ion power
逼近邂逅灶神星和谷神星
to close in on an encounter with Vesta and Ceres,
那两颗我们太阳系的小行星带里最大的天体
two of the largest objects in our solar system's asteroid belt.
离子驱动器如此强大的原因之一
One of the things that makes ion drives so powerful
就在于它们具有对燃料的最有效利用
is they have the most effective use of fuel,
在太空中 不存在摩擦
and in space, there's no friction.
没东西让你慢下来
There's nothing to slow you down.
因此用来加速这些离子的所有能量
And so all the energy used to accelerate these ions
都能够变成前进的速度
can go into forward velocity,
你可以持之以恒 假以时日
and you can just keep, over huge periods of time,
加速 加速 再加速
accelerating and accelerating and accelerating.
传统的化学火箭燃烧迅速 喧闹 炙热
Traditional chemical rockets burn fast, loud, and hot.
离子推进系统 另一方面
Ion propulsion systems, on the other hand,
用于长途推进上
are in it for the long haul.
因而离子驱动器不光是科幻
So ion drives are both science fiction
如今也成了科学事实
and, today, science fact.
离开我们太阳系的太空探测器
Between space probes headed out of our solar system
以及电视和无线电波中 有些已经离开了
and TV and radio waves, which have already left,
人类宣告了自己在宇宙间的存在
humans have announced their presence to the universe.
我们已经送出了信使
We have sent out missions
携带的唱片包含了笑声
with records containing the sounds of laughter
心跳声
and the beating of the heart,
男性和女性的解剖图
with anatomical diagrams of men and women.
这些是物理使节 我们将它们送往星际
These are physical ambassadors that we've sent out among the stars.
卡尔 萨根N多年前问过
Carl Sagan asked the question many years ago,
谁代表地球发话？
"Who speaks for Earth?"
好 最后 我认为我们都代表地球
Well, ultimately, I guess we all speak for Earth,
我希望我们更多一点谨慎
and I wish we'd been a little more circumspect
更多一点思考 把各种信息
or a little more thoughtful about the kinds of messages
和想法用我们的电台和电视节目送入太空
and ideas we're sending out into space with our radio and television programs.
迄今为止 我们的广播没有回音
So far, our broadcasts have gone unanswered.
但要是有所变化呢？
But what if that changes?
科幻充满了外星人来到我们中间所发生的故事
Science fiction is filled with tales of what happens when aliens arrive among us.
我认为我们会发现生命确实存在
I think we're going to find life out there definitely.
如果是那样 我们有没有任何机遇呢？
And if that happens, do we stand any chance?
抑或我们注定要被彻底抹去
Or are we destined to be wiped from existence,
被先进的外星智慧所消灭呢？
exterminated by an advanced alien intellect?
它们说它们虔诚地走来
They say they come in peace.
它们打碎了我们的星球
They leave our planet in pieces.
打最早的科幻小说开始
Since the earliest science fiction stories,
某些主题重复着引人注目的频率
some themes have recurred with remarkable frequency,
或许都莫过于这个话题 -
perhaps none so much as this one--
外来入侵
alien invasions.
外星人成群抵达地球大肆破坏
Alien hordes arriving at the Earth and wreaking havoc,
只是出自戏剧的视角
just from a dramatic point of view,
那本身就比友善的外星人前来解决
that's inherently more interesting than friendly aliens
我们所有的问题来的有趣
coming and solving all of our problems for us.
据信这始于H G 威尔斯 和《星际战争》
Think it started with H.G. Wells and "The War of the Worlds,"
他写那本小说是作为对当时的英国殖民主义的批判
and he wrote that novel as a kind of criticism of British colonialism at the time.
电影《第九区》
The movie "District 9"
一睹人类天生有多猜疑
takes a look at how humanity is inherently suspicious
天生在许多方面 种族主义有多
and inherently, in many ways, racist
防范我们尚不了解的东西
against the things that we don't understand.
外星人 我们对其的不了解是否
And aliens, well, what do we not understand
就如同我们不了解其他世界的生命那样呢？
as much as we don't understand life on other worlds?
天文学家长期以来一直试图确定
Astronomers have long been trying to determine
是否有合理科学的方法来回答这个古老的问题 -
if there's a plausible, scientific way to answer the age-old question,
我们孤独吗？
"Are we alone?"
智慧生命在宇宙间常见吗？
How common is intelligent life in the universe?
费米悖论
The Fermi Paradox,
取名来自首次提出问题的物理学家恩里科 费米
named for a question first posed by physicist Enrico Fermi,
试图阐明关于外星生命的难题
attempts to illuminate a conundrum about extraterrestrial life.
如果外星生命在宇宙间并不罕见
If intelligent life in the universe is common,
那么它们又在哪里呢？
then where are they?
好 如果它们不在这 就有可能不在任何地方
Well, if they're not here, they're probably not anywhere.
所以我想要么我们是独一无二的
So I think either we're unique,
这本身就有点让人惊讶
which is in and of itself kind of astonishing,
要么就是我们这样的智慧生命并不是那么普遍
or intelligent life like us is just not that common.
好 问题可以倒过来问
Well, the question can be reversed.
为何它们还没有发现我们？
Why haven't they detected us?
我们对那已相当了解了
And we understand that fairly well.
把我们的存在广播给
What would broadcast our existence
宇宙其他地方的是我们的无线电发射
to the rest of the universe is our radio emissions.
我们自上世纪20年代开始
And we've really been broadcasting
实际上一直在以适当的量进行广播
in any reasonable amount since about the 1920s.
因此那意味着我们的发射
So that means that our emissions,
以光速向外发送
which radiate outwards at the speed of light,
已经走过了约90光年
have reached about 90 light-years.
这样我们就有了90光年半径的球形
So we have a sphere of 90 light-years of radius
其中的行星 恒星以及文明就会发现我们
of planets and stars, civilizations that could detect us.
那并不很大
That's not very big.
我们的星系从一头到另一头是10万光年
Our galaxy is 100,000 light-years from end to end.
因此要是有成百数千个文明存在
So if there were hundreds, thousands of civilizations out there,
也许就只有一两个能够在
it might be that only one or two have been able to detect us
我们不停的广播过程中发现我们
in the time we've been broadcasting.
它们或许还没来得及回复信息
And they may not have had time to send a hello message back.
另一个潜在的问题 - 信号丢失
Another possible problem-- loss of signal.
电波送出地球后 其强度会衰减
As radio waves spread out from Earth, they fall off in intensity,
最终融合进宇宙背景之中
eventually blending in to the cosmic background.
如果另一个星球上的人要听到我们的信息
If someone on another planet is going to hear our transmissions,
它们可能必须要相对靠近些
they might have to be relatively close.
那么会有多少文明会调到我们的电台节目和重播呢？
So how many civilizations might be tuning in to our radio shows and reruns?
那是天文学家弗兰克 德雷克
That's a question astronomer Frank Drake
试图解答的著名的问题
famously tried to answer.
约50年前 弗兰克 德雷克 射电天文学家
Around 50 years ago, Frank Drake, a radio astronomer,
一直在考虑宇宙生命的可能性
was considering the possibility for life in the universe,
他推出了首个搜寻地外文明计划
and he launched the first SETI program,
第一次尝试利用射电望远镜
the first attempt to use a radio telescope
来监听来自其他星球的信号
to listen for signals from other stars.
德雷克一直在想
So Drake was wondering,
我成功的机会有多少？
well, what are my chances of success here?
我们星系里会有多少文明的存在？
How many civilizations might there be in our galaxy?
和其他优秀的天文学家一样
So, like any good astronomer,
他做了一点粗略的估算
he did a little back-of-the-envelope calculation,
他建了一个等式 基本上是说
and he created an equation that basically said,
好 我们来计算一下
all right, here's how we calculate
我们星系里的文明数量
the number of civilizations in our galaxy.
我们星系里会有多少恒星
How many stars are there in our galaxy
能够具有类似地球的行星呢？
that are capable of having planets that are like the Earth?
那些恒星中有多少确实具有地球这样的行星呢？
How many of those stars do have planets like Earth?
在那些类地行星中又有多少
On how many of those Earth-like planets
确实有生命的发展呢？ 等等
did life actually develop? And so on.
如果你是个乐观主义者 你就会发现有好多好多
If you're an optimist, you find that there are lots and lots
智能 结社的文明
of intelligent, communicating civilizations
存在于我们的银河系里
in our Milky Way Galaxy.
如果你是个悲观主义者 那么 你很容易发现
If you're a pessimist, however, you can easily find
一百万个我们这样的星系里头只有一个
that only one in a million galaxies like ours
有可能存在智能
might have intelligence.
因此要是你是悲观主义者
So, if you're a pessimist,
我们就可能是我们银河系里的独生子
we may well be the only ones in our Milky Way Galaxy.
如果一个庞大的邪恶外星力量冲我们而来
If a massive and malevolent alien force heads our way,
地球的最佳防御是什么呢？
what is Earth's best defense?
拯救我们的情况之一就是太空旅行并不快
One of the things that saves us is space travel is slow.
我们会获得警告 它们来了
We'll have warning that they're coming.
我们会看到它们 或许会有好多天的警告
We'll see them with probably many days' warning
因为它们穿过太阳系时
as they pass through the solar system
看上去就像又一个巨大的小行星或彗星
looking like another giant asteroid or comet
从外太阳系闯入
coming in from the outer solar system.
随着它们的到来 问题是 它们要干嘛？
As they get here, the question is, what do they do?
难道它们真的就是《独立日》里的外星人
Are they really the "Independence Day" aliens
进来占领我们的大都市
that come in and sit over our major cities
威胁所有的生命 如我们预料的那样？
and threaten all life as we know it?
还是它们只是登陆
Or do they simply land
向我们派发书籍和药物呢？
and offer us their books and their medicine?
要是那成为一场街头战争的话 或许拯救地球
If it becomes a street fight, perhaps Earth will be saved
要用上受科幻启发的武器了
using weapons inspired by science fiction.
从卢克 天行者优雅的光剑
From Luke Skywalker's elegant lightsaber
到上千场周末下午场电影里用到的激光枪
to the laser guns used in a thousand Saturday matinees,
科幻中并不缺手持武器
there's no shortage of handheld weapons in sci-fi.
多年来科幻里的武器已经有了骇人的装置
Weaponry in science fiction for years has had some sort of stun setting.
《星际迷航》里的光枪
The phasers in "Star Trek,"
《空间 1999》里的钉枪
the staple guns in "Space: 1999,"
都会致人昏迷不醒 但不会让人丧命
will render somebody unconscious, but not kill them.
如今的科技在那种东西上正变得越来越好
Technology today is getting better at that sort of thing.
受科幻的启发
Inspired by science fiction,
武器研究一直在开发
weapons researchers continue to develop
种种手段去影响人的行为
a variety of ways to affect someone's behavior
无需使用粗糙的子弹去洞穿他们
without blowing a hole through them using a crude projectile.
美军已研发出主动拒止系统
The U.S. military have developed the Active Denial System,
系统旨在激发再见效果
a system designed to elicit the goodbye effect.
那个就是大型微波发射机
What this is, is a huge microwave transmitter.
你发射它来驱散人群
You shoot this to disperse crowds.
人们确实会感到皮肤上火烧火燎
People literally feel like their skin's on fire
他们就退避三舍了
and they say goodbye.
其它军事项目利用电力
Other military projects harness the power of electricity,
基于泰瑟枪技术来发射非致命的震慑
building on Taser technology to deliver a nonlethal jolt.
一个简单的现象 诸如电流 当然啦
A simple phenomenon, such as electricity, of course,
是科学事实
is science fact,
已经引出了科幻中的许多想法
one that has sparked many ideas in science fiction,
包括提供能量给
including providing the power
史上最著名的时间机器之一
for one of the most famous time machines ever built.
让你的1 21千兆瓦待命
Have your 1.21 jigowatts standing by,
点燃通量电容器
fire up the flux capacitor,
准备来一趟时光倒流之旅
and get ready to take a trip back in time.
时光旅行
Time travel.
有可能
It is possible,
根据20世纪两位最伟大的科学大脑 -
according to two of the 20th century's greatest scientific minds--
阿尔伯特 爱因斯坦 他著名的方程式
Albert Einstein, whose famous equations
一点都不排除时光旅行的可能性
did nothing to preclude the possibility of time travel,
还有埃米特 布朗博士 通量电容器的发明者
and Dr. Emmett Brown, inventor of the flux capacitor.
根本区别在哪？
The big difference?
爱因斯坦的时间机器只能单向行驶
Einstein's time machine only goes in one direction
依据来自大量的科学论证
and is supported by mounds of scientific evidence.
我们知道根据狭义相对论和广义相对论
We know from special relativity and general relativity
时光旅行是完全有可能的 -
that time travel is absolutely possible--
时光旅行到未来
time travel to the future.
如果你前往邻近的恒星
If you traveled to a nearby star
速度达到光速的较大比例
at a sizeable fraction of the speed of light
回来时 你会发现地球上的人们
and came back, you would find that people on Earth
比你老很多了
have aged a lot more than you have.
相对论实际上允许往前的时光旅行
Relativity actually allows time travel forward.
《巴克 罗杰斯在25世纪》演的没错
"Buck Rogers in the 25th Century" got it right,
《仙女座》演的没错
"Andromeda" got it right.
布朗博士的时间机器
Doc Brown's time machine
在时间上能同时往前往后
goes both forward and backward in time,
根据物理定律 那是行不通的
and according to the laws of physics, that's a no-no.
是这样吗？
Or is it?
穿梭回过去
Traveling into the past
似乎并不违背任何物理学基本定律
doesn't seem to violate any fundamental laws of physics.
事实上 有一些方案
And, in fact, there are some schemes
物理学家所讨论到的
that physicists have talked about
似乎提供了一个旅行回过去的机会
that seem to provide an opportunity to travel into the past.
以某种方式围绕着黑洞穿行似乎能够做到
Traveling in a certain way around a black hole might do it.
虫洞无疑能转换成时间机器
Wormholes could conceivably be converted into time machines.
如果你拿虫洞的一头
If you take one end of a wormhole,
将其加速到接近光速
accelerate it to close to the speed of light,
将其送出数百光年
send it out many hundreds of light-years
让其回到你所在位置的附近
and bring it back to close to where you started,
那好 虫洞的那一头
well, that end of the wormhole
就长期存在于另外一头的过去中了
exists permanently in the past at the other end.
因此 有可能 通过穿越虫洞
So, presumably, by flying through the wormhole,
你就可以旅行回过去了
you could travel into the past.
听起来简单 但科学家称没有已知的方法
Sounds simple, but scientists say there's no known way
稳定能量场来打造这样一个虫洞
to stabilize the energy field that would make up such a wormhole.
另一个问题 -
And another problem--
旅行回过去 你有造成悖论的风险
travel to the past and you risk causing a paradox.
时间旅行中的祖父悖论
The grandfather paradox in time travel
就是你回到过去杀死你的祖父
is that you go back in time and kill your grandfather
此时你的母亲或父亲尚未出生
before your mother or father was born,
那么这就意味着你就不可能来到人世了
and this then means that you couldn't have possibly come into existence.
那么你又怎么能够回到过去
But then how could you have gone back in time
干掉你的祖父呢？
and killed your grandfather?
那是个逻辑悖论
It's a logical paradox.
有人曾经说过
Other people have said,
啊 要知道 没准有办法绕开这个问题
well, you know, maybe there's a way around this problem.
量子力学有一个方法
There is a way of looking at quantum mechanics
叫做量子力学的多重世界解释
called the Many-Worlds Interpretation of Quantum Mechanics.
量子力学的许多解释之一称
One of the many interpretations of quantum mechanics says
每做出一个决定 宇宙就分裂了
that every time a decision is made, the universe splits.
每当我发送一个光子经过裂缝
Every time I send a photon of light through a slit
它就向一个方向跑
and it goes in one direction,
而在另外一个宇宙里 它跑向另一个方向
there's another universe where it goes in another direction.
我在这个宇宙里泼出我的咖啡
Every time I spill my coffee in this universe,
而另一个宇宙里 我的咖啡却安然无恙
there's another universe where my coffee remains safe.
根据这个量子力学的多重世界解释
According to this Many-Worlds Interpretation of Quantum Mechanics,
一切可能出现的东西 都已经发生在了某处
anything that could've been, has happened somewhere.
一切都可能 都会存在于多重宇宙的某个地方
And anything that can be, will be, somewhere in the multiverse.
因此确实有无数个宇宙
And so there are literally countless universes
不停地分裂出我们的宇宙
splitting off from our own
分分秒秒 时时刻刻
every second of every day of every year.
如果是那样的话
And if that's the case,
人们就会认为旅行回到了过去
then people argue that, well, traveling back in time,
你可以回去杀死你的祖父
you could go back and kill your grandfather,
你还活着 哈 怎么样？
and you'd still be alive. Well, how is that?
啊 你只是来到了另一个宇宙
Well, you just traveled into a different universe.
如果时间旅行时可能的 有一件事是肯定的
If time travel is possible, one thing is certain.
它需要大量的能量
It's going to take a lot of energy.
在《回到未来》中 博士进行时间旅行时
In "Back to the Future," Doc achieves time travel
他将他的德劳瑞恩汽车的动力提高到了1 21千兆瓦
when he gets his DeLorean powered up with 1.21 jigowatts
达到了时速88英里
and achieves a speed of 88 miles per hour.
那整个就是天方夜谭
That's all just complete fantasy.
穿梭回过去所需的实际能量
The actual energy required for travel backwards in time,
也就是 速度超过光速
that is, travel faster than the speed of light,
是无穷大的 甚至大得我们难以言表
is infinite or even more than infinite from what we can tell,
或者需要某种虫洞
or requires some sort of a wormhole
或其它的快捷方式来穿越宇宙
or other passage shortcut through the universe.
1 21千兆瓦是做不到的
1.21 jigowatts just isn't going to do it.
时速88英里是做不到的
88 miles an hour just isn't going to do it.
有时 电影学科会胜过科学学科的
Sometimes, movie science trumps science science.
通量电容器是什么玩意 其原理何在？
What is a flux capacitor, and how does it work?
告诉你 我一点都不知道
You know, I have no idea whatsoever.
《回到未来》三部曲
The "Back to the Future" trilogy
还表演了飞行汽车飞驰在空中高速公路上
also shows flying cars speeding down aerial highways
就在并不遥远的2015年
in the now not-so-far-off year of 2015.
许多科幻故事不着边际
Many tales of science fiction miss the mark
如果靠它来预测未来的话
when it comes to predicting the future.
关于回头观看老科幻的令人惊叹的事情之一
One of the amazing things about going back and looking at old sci-fi
就是人们从来没有真正想过 我们生活不可分割的组成部分
is people never really imagined how integral a part of our lives
居然会是电脑
computers would become,
我们大家居然都有自己的手持设备
how all of us would have our own handheld devices,
我们自己的笔记本 自己的台式机
our own laptops, our own desktops,
我们所做的一切 在很多方面
and everything we do would, in many ways,
要依靠技术来解决
be mediated through the technology.
甚至小孩子现在在很多情况下都有自己的笔记本
Even small children now have their own laptops in many cases.
你在科幻中没有看到这情况
And you don't see this in the sci-fi.
但另一方面
But in other ways,
科幻与科学事实之间的差异
the distinctions between the worlds of science fiction and science fact
正逐年变得越来越模糊了
are becoming more and more blurred with each passing year.
毕竟 柯克和斯波克并不是唯一的人
After all, Kirk and Spock aren't the only ones
持有袖珍通讯设备
with a pocket-sized communications device
能够让你与世界各地的人进行沟通
that can connect you with anyone else on the planet.
博曼尼斯呼叫格雷齐尔 博曼尼斯呼叫格雷齐尔 听到请回话
Bormanis to Grazier. Bormanis to Grazier. Come in.
关于通讯技术的话题 -
Under the topic of communications technology--
对不起
Excuse me.
稍等 安德烈 我没空
Not now, Andre. I'm busy.
通讯就是科学超越了科幻的一个方面
Communications is a place where science has outpaced science fiction.
翻盖式手机就像是原始的发报机
The cell phones that flip open like the original communicator
实际上具有比发报机更多的选项
actually have more options than the communicator did.
我的意思是 你见过斯波克先生玩俄罗斯方块吗？
I mean, did you ever see Mr. Spock playing Tetris?
你见过柯克船长被短信打扰过吗？
Did you ever see Captain Kirk interrupted by a text message?
没有
No.
科学胜过了科幻
Science trumps science fiction.
谁会料到呢？
Who'd have thought it?
40年前貌似神奇的东西
What seemed miraculous 40 years ago
如今已装进了我们的口袋
is carried around in our pockets today.
科幻是梦幻的科学
Science fiction is the dreaming side of science.
那是想象
It's the imagination,
但你不能只有科学而没有想象
but you can't have science itself without imagination.
科学需要灵感
Science needs inspiration.
它需要灵光闪现的时刻 啊哈
It needs that eureka moment, that "aha!"
我认为科幻
And I think science fiction
帮助科学家创造了那样的时刻
helps create those moments for scientists.
随着时代的推进
With each passing decade,
未来幻想故事的创造者都进一步推进了想象力
creators of fantastic tales of the future push the imagination further,
因为人们总是好奇于明天
because man will always wonder about tomorrow,
甚至在它来临后
even after it arrives,
矛盾还是交织在科幻和科学事实的世界里
a paradox befitting the intertwined worlds